this is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in the public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this
recording by J Hall the Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter 4 The Road
Through the Forest After a few hours the road began to be rough, and the walking
grew so difficult that the Scarecrow often stumbled over the yellow bricks,
which were here very uneven. Sometimes, indeed, they were broken or missing
altogether, leaving holes that Toto jumped across and Dorothy walked around.
As for the Scarecrow, having no brains, he walks straight ahead, and slow stepped
into the holes and fell at full length on the hard bricks. It never hurt him,
however, and Dorothy would pick him up and set him upon his feet again, while he
joined her and laughing merrily at his own mishap. The farms were not nearly so
well cared for here as they were farther back. There were fewer houses and fewer
fruit trees, and the farther they went the more dismal and lonesome the country
became. At noon they sat down by the roadside, near a little brook, and Dorothy
opened her basket and got out some bread.
She offered a piece to the Scarecrow, but he refused.
“I am never hungry,” he said, “and it is a
lucky thing I am not, for my mouth is only painted, and if I should cut a hole
in it so I could eat, the straw I'm stuffed with would come out, and that
would spoil the shape of my head.” Dorothy saw at once that this was true
and so she nodded and went on eating her bread. “Tell me something about yourself
and the country you came from,” said the Scarecrow, when she had finished her
dinner. So she told him all about Kansas, and how gray everything was there, and
how the cyclone had carried her to this queer Land of Oz. The Scarecrow listened
carefully, and said, “I cannot understand why you would wish to leave this
beautiful country and go back to the dry, gray place you call Kansas.” “That is
because you have no brains” answered the girl. “No matter how dreary and gray our homes
we people of flesh and blood would rather live there than in any other
country, be it ever so beautiful. There is no place like home.”
The Scarecrow side Of course I cannot understand it,” he said. “If your heads were
stuffed with straw, like mine, you would probably all live in the beautiful
places, and then Kansas would have no people at all. It is fortunate for Kansas
that you have brains.” “Won’t you tell me a story, while we are resting ask the child.
The Scarecrow looked at her reproachfully, and answered: “My life has
been so short that I really know nothing whatever.
I was only made day before yesterday.
What happened in the world before that time is all unknown to me. Luckily, when
the farmer made my head, one of the first things he did was to paint my ears, so
that I heard what was going on. There was another Munchkin with him, and the first
thing I heard was the farmer saying, ‘How do you like those ears?’ “‘They aren’t
straight,’” answered the other. “‘Never mind,’” said the farmer their ears just the same,’”
which was true enough. “‘Now I’ll make the eyes,’” said the farmer. So he painted my
right eye, and as soon as it was finished I found myself looking at him and at
everything around me with a great deal of curiosity, for this was my first
glimpse of the world. “‘That’s a rather pretty I remarked the Munchkin who was
watching the farmer. “‘Blue paint is just the color for eyes.’ “‘I think I’ll make the
other a little bigger,’” said the farmer.
And when the second eye was done I could see much better than before. Then he made
my nose in my mouth. But I did not speak,
because at the time I didn’t know what a
mouth was for. I had the fun of watching them make my body in my arms and legs;
and when they fastened on my head, at last, I felt very proud, for I thought I
was just as good a man as anyone. “‘This fellow will scare the crows fast enough,’
said the farmer. ‘He looks just like a man.’
“‘Why, he is a man,’ said the other, and I quite agreed with him. The farmer carried
me under his arm to the cornfield, and set me up on a tall stick, where you
found me. He and his friend soon after walked away and left me alone. “I did not
like to be deserted this way. So I tried to walk after them. But my feet would not
touch the ground, and I was to stay on that pole. It was a lonely
life to lead, for I had nothing to think of, having been made such a short while
before. Many crows and other birds flew into the cornfield, but as soon as they
saw me they flew away again, thinking I was a Munchkin; and this pleased me and
made me feel that I was quite an important person. By and by an old crow
flew near me, and after looking at me carefully he perched upon my shoulder
and said: “‘I wonder if that farmer thought to fool me in this clumsy manner. Any
crow of sense could see that you are only stuffed with straw.’ Then he hopped
down at my feet and ate all the corn he wanted. The other birds, seeing he was not
harmed by me, came to eat the corn too, so
in a short time there was a great flock
of them about me. “I felt sad at this, for it showed I was not such a good
Scarecrow after all; but the old crow comforted me, saying, ‘If you only had
brains in your head you would be as good
a man as any of them, and a better man than some of them. Brains are the only
things worth having in this world, no matter whether one is a crow or a man.’
“After the crows had gone I thought this over, and decided I would try hard to get
some brains. By good luck you came along and pulled me off the stake, and from
what you say I'm sure the Great Oz will
give me some brains as soon as we get to the Emerald City.”
“I hope so,” said Dorothy earnestly, “since you seem anxious to have them.” “Oh, yes; I
am anxious,” returned the Scarecrow. “It is such an uncomfortable feeling to know
one is a fool.” “Well,” said the girl, “let us go.” And she handed the basket to the
Scarecrow. There were no fences at all by the roadside now, and the land was rough
and untilled. Toward evening they came to a great forest, where the trees grew so
big and close together that their branches met over the road of yellow
brick. It was almost dark under the trees, for the branches shut out the daylight;
but the travelers did not stop, and went on into the forest. “If this road goes in,
it must come out,” said the Scarecrow, “and as the Emerald City is at the other end
of the road, we must go wherever it leads us.” “Anyone
would know that,” said Dorothy. “Certainly; that is why I know it,” returned the Scarecrow.
“If it required brains to figure it out, I never should have said it.” After an hour
so the light faded away, and they found themselves stumbling along in the
darkness. Dorothy could not see it all, but Toto could, for some dogs see very
well on the dark; and the Scarecrow declared he could see as well as by day.
So she took a hold of his arm and managed to get along fairly well. “If you
see any houses or any place where we can pass the night,” she said, “you must tell me;
for it is very uncomfortable walking in the dark.” Soon after the Scarecrow stopped. “I see a
little college at the right of us,” he said, “built of logs and branches. Shall we
go there?” “Yes, indeed,” answered the child. “I am all tired out.” So the Scarecrow led
her through the trees until they reached the cottage, and Dorothy entered and
found a bed of dried leaves in one corner. She laid down at once, and with
Toto beside her soon fell into a sound sleep.
The Scarecrow, who was never tired, stood up in another corner and waited
patiently until morning came end of Chapter 4